So, owing to the fact that the federal
government under the Articles of
Confederation was about as effective as
trying to catch a fart in a colander, it
is now time to get ourselves a new
Constitution. And that's what this video
is about. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, so I ended the last video talking
about the glaring weaknesses of the
federal government created by the
Articles of Confederation. And it was
Shea's rebellion that convinced folks
that something drastic needed to happen
so that more angry and rebellious
farmers didn't destroy this fresh-faced
baby republic. So in 1787 55 delegates
met in Philadelphia to participate in
the constitutional convention. Now the
main question they came to answer was
this. Is there a way to revise and
strengthen the articles or should we
draft an entirely new constitution? Now
the majority of the delegates attended
the convention with the intent of
revising the articles. But a strong and
vocal minority aimed to persuade them to
draft a new constitution altogether. And
it wasn't long before this minority
convinced the convention to pursue a new
constitution. But in order to achieve
that end, debates, negotiations, and
compromises needed to occur. And hey,
I'm as big a fan of compromise as the
next guy. But the one thing I will not
compromise on is getting you an A in
your class and a five on your exam in
May. And so I want to help you learn all
that you need to know. And to do that, I
created my A Push Heimler review guide,
which has everything you need to study
for your exams as fast as possible. So
if that's something you're into, check
that link below. Okay, so back to the
compromises needed to create a new
constitution. Now, as I mentioned
before, the main problem with the
articles was that it created a federal
government that was too weak and state
governments that were comparatively too
strong. And while it certainly avoided
the tyranny of centralized power, the
federal government simply could not meet
the needs of the new and growing
republic. Therefore, in debating the
need for a new constitution, the main
question became, how do we strengthen
the federal government without giving it
so much power that it becomes a
tyrannical turd? And the answer that
came after months of debate and
compromise was that this new government
would achieve this balance by relying on
three basic principles. First, the
constitution would avoid federal tyranny
by means of the separation of powers.
Now the federal government under the
articles invested federal power in a
single branch of government namely the
legislative branch which is to say the
congress. But the new constitution would
seek to balance and restrain power by
dividing it among three branches. The
legislative branch would be responsible
for creating laws and that duty would be
carried out by congress. The executive
branch would be responsible for
enforcing the laws and that duty would
be discharged by a president. And then
the judicial branch would be responsible
for interpreting the constitutionality
of laws and that duty would fall to the
supreme court. And that leads us to the
second means by which the power of the
new federal government would be
restrained. Namely through checks and
balances. And basically this is the idea
that each branch of government had power
that could check and balance or you know
restrain the power of the other
branches. That way no one branch could
become too powerful and dominate the
rest. For example, the president had the
power to veto legislation sent by
Congress. And then Congress had the
power to approve or disapprove a
presidential appointment to the Supreme
Court. Then the court had the power to
declare a law of Congress
unconstitutional and thus null and void.
Now, I should mention that the power I
just mentioned from the court is known
as judicial review and it's not actually
written into the constitution. But it
would become clear in a later court
decision in 1803, but we'll think about
that in the next year. Regardless, the
point is in order to strengthen the
federal government while simultaneously
keeping that power in check, the framers
of the constitution made use of
separation of powers and checks and
balances. And finally, the third
constitutional mechanism to restrain the
power of the federal government was to
create a system structured by
federalism. Now, by definition,
federalism describes a system in which
power is shared between federal and
state governments. Now, let's stop right
here for a hot second because this is an
oft confused topic for students. Now,
I've been flapping my mouth hole about
the federal government and state
governments. And when I say federalism,
a lot of you think I'm talking about the
federal government. And I don't blame
you cuz that's what it sounds like. But
smack that error right out of your brain
folds because federalism only describes
the sharing of political power between a
federal government and state government.
Just the sharing of power, that's it. So
all that to say the constitution created
a federalist system of governments in
which any power that was not explicitly
granted to the federal government was
reserved for the states which is a
guarantee enshrined in the 10th
amendment. For example, the power to
oversee elections is reserved for the
states. But then the power to declare
war belongs only to the federal
government. Then there are a handful of
concurrent powers which both federal and
state governments share like for example
taxation. So the point is power shared
tyranny avoided. Now that's basically
how the constitution eventually turned
out. But getting to that finish line
required an enormous amount of debate
and compromise over several key issues.
And I'll mention three that you need to
know. First, there was a debate over
representation in the federal
government. In other words, since the
new government grew right out of the
soil of enlightenment thought, one of
the most fundamental principles of
political power was that it belonged to
the people. But the framers of the
Constitution were in no way friendly to
the idea of pure democracy in which
everyone had a say about everything. No.
By their reckoning, most Americans were
idiots. the number increasing rapidly,
the further one got from the
constitutional convention hall in
Philadelphia. Therefore, they aimed to
create a republic in which the people's
voice would be represented by a few
educated elected politicians. And on
that idea, basically everyone in the
convention agreed. But when it came time
to figure out exactly how representation
would work, things got uh contentious.
Now, there were two basic plans that
were put forward. The first was the
Virginia plan, which argued that
representation in the new Congress would
be reckoned by population. In other
words, the more population a state had,
the more representatives it would have
in Congress. That sounds fair, right?
Like Virginia has metric buttloadades of
people, so shouldn't they have a larger
voice in the government? But smaller
states were about as excited for this
plan as they welcomed a healthy dose of
inner thigh chafe after a long day at a
water park. And that's not hard to
understand either. Like if the biggest
states had the most representation, then
nothing that the smaller states wanted
would ever come to pass. Therefore, as a
counter proposal to the Virginia plan,
we got the New Jersey plan, which argued
that representation in Congress should
be equal, like every state gets a single
representative. And that, of course, was
intolerable to the large states. So
after much debate they came up with the
great compromise otherwise known as the
Connecticut compromise and it created
two houses of Congress instead of one or
if you want to get fancy about it you
could say they created a biccameal
legislature. Now the lower house was
called the house of representatives in
which representation would be reckoned
by population. The members of this body
would be elected directly by the people.
The upper house was the senate in which
representation would be equal. So two
senators per state. And at this point
senators would not be elected by the
people but instead by state legislators.
But that would change with a
constitutional amendment in 1913 that
mandated that senators be elected just
like representatives in the house by
popular vote. Okay. Now, the second
compromise you should know was a result
of the debate over how the president
would be elected. Should the people do
the electing or should the states or
should congress? Well, the compromise
was the electoral college in which each
state chooses a number of electors that
corresponds to the number of their
congressional representatives. And it is
those electors who vote for the
president. And if you're confused by
that, then you're basically the same as
every American in every presidential
election since the constitution was
written. But anyway, the third debate of
the constitutional convention was about
slavery and two compromises came out of
this discussion. And I guess it goes
without saying that they patently did
not consult any enslaved person and ask
for their opinions on this matter. But
you know, yeah, whatever. So, first was
the debate regarding how enslaved people
would count for representation in the
Congress. States in the north that held
relatively few enslaved people thought
that they should not be counted
whatsoever. But states in the south that
had huge populations of enslaved people
thought that they should be counted and
thus add more house seats to their
total. And the compromise they
eventually reached was known as the
three-fifths compromise, which allowed
for, you know, 3-fifths of the enslaved
population to count towards
representation. Now, hold on. Let me
just make extra sure that you realize
that this was not a debate over whether
enslaved blacks could vote or have any
kind of representation for their own
interests. That is a big heck no.
Really, it was about population
distribution between the North and the
South. See, the South with his massive
plantations had far less population than
the North. But what they did have was a
massive population of enslaved blacks
working those plantations. Therefore,
the southern delegates wanted those
enslaved people counted for the sake of
representation so that they could have
more seats in the house than their white
population alone would afford them.
Okay. Then the second compromise over
slavery had to do with the importation
of enslaved people from Africa. And
basically the agreement was that
Congress couldn't touch the slave trade
for 20 years after ratification after
which the international slave trade
would be abolished. Okay. Now that all
the compromises were hammered out and
the constitution was finished, it was
time to send that sweet bippy to the
states for ratification. Now only nine
out of 13 states were required to ratify
the document in order for it to replace
the Articles of Confederation. But once
that whole process began, a fierce
debate arose between two factions. On
the one side, you had the Federalists
who argued for ratification and they
were generally made up of socially
powerful people who for the most part
lived in cities. Their main argument for
ratification was that the federal
government needed to be strengthened if
the new republic was going to be able to
survive and thrive economically and
politically. And essentially they
maintained that unity was the only way
to ensure the survival of the new
republic. and that the sheer diversity
of interests represented by such a vast
population would prevent the tyranny of
the majority. Now, the most prominent
Federalists were Alexander Hamilton,
John J, and James Madison. And in order
to argue for ratification, they
published a flurry of essays in New York
newspapers, which together became known
as the Federalist Papers. In these
essays, they expounded on each article
and clause of the Constitution and tried
to prove that a stronger federal
government would not lead to tyranny and
would benefit the lots of all Americans.
But on the other side of the debate were
the anti-federalists who argued against
ratification. Now, they were smart
enough to realize that there were
problems with the Articles of
Confederation, but from their
perspective, strengthening the federal
government would only lead right back to
the tyranny problems they had with
Britain before the revolution. And more
than that, on the level of principle,
they didn't believe that a central
government could effectively address the
needs of all the various diverse regions
and people that made up the new nation.
And one of their biggest gripes was that
the Constitution had no bill of rights
that explicitly listed the liberties
guaranteed to Americans. After all, many
state governments had such a list. and
the fact that it was absent from the
document creating the federal government
seemed real suspicious to them. But the
federalist argued that the inclusion of
a bill of rights was just unnecessary
because the system of checks and
balances would prevent federal
infringement of individual liberties.
But ultimately, the arguments of the
Federalist won the day and by June of
1788, enough states had ratified the
document and it became the law of the
land. However, the only way the
federalists were able to achieve this
was to pacify federalist fears and
promise to include a bill of rights soon
after ratification. And that, my dear
pupil, is how you get a big boy federal
government in the new United States.
Well, okay. You can click here to watch
my other Unit 3 videos, or you can click
here to grab my A Push Himler review
guide. And I'm glad you stopped by, and
I'll catch you on the flip-flop. I'm
Lar.